Animation Number 1
Araragi-senpai.
（扇(おうぎ)）阿良々木(あららぎ)先輩
Did you know there's a moment where every traffic light in an intersection turns red?
交差点の信号が全て赤になる
瞬間があるのを ご存じですか？
I recall all of Ougi-chan's words in one go
Animation Number 10
（阿良々木）ん？　何だそりゃ？
What's that? When the manufacturer checks it?
業者さんに点検でもされるときか？
No no, it happens much more frequently. Even you've seen it on a daily basis, Araragi-senpai.
（扇）
いやいや
もっと頻繁にあるんですよ
阿良々木先輩だって
毎日のように見ているはずです
A daily basis? I don't recall seeing anything like that.
（阿良々木）毎日のように…
いや そんなもん見た覚えはねえぞ
I mean, if that happened all the time, there'd be traffic accidents all over.
つうか そんな現象が
日常的に起きていたら
あちこち交通事故で大変だぜ
They make sure it happens all the time so there won't be traffic accidents all over.
（扇）
あちこち交通事故で
大変にしないために
そんな現象を
日常的に起こしてるんですよ
You really don't get it. You're such a fool.
分かっていませんね
（扇）この愚か者は
It's a very simple story when you look behind the scenes.
いやいや 種を明かせば
簡単な話なんです 阿良々木先輩
After vertical signals turn red and until horizontal ones turn green...
縦の信号が赤になってから
横の信号が青になるまでの間に
Naoetsu High School
...every signal always has a three-second time lag.
どの信号にも 必ず３秒の
タイムラグがあるんですよ
Pedestrians Only
Vehicles Only
Naoetsu High School
Priority Traffic for Naoetsu High School
For Pedestrans
And Bicycles Only
Three seconds...
３秒…
That's not a "moment." No one takes three seconds to blink.
瞬間じゃねえじゃねえか
３秒単位で
まばたきするヤツなんていねえよ
Don't look for faults in my logic. Your personality really is the worst.
（扇）
揚げ足を取らないでくださいよ
性格が最悪ですね 阿良々木先輩
Various Stock Averages
63.82441
88.5611
At Closing
Opening 01.82351
Peak 63.54461
Bottom 52.83661
Today
Last 3 Months
In other words, everything comes to a halt. You could call it the blank three seconds of an intersection.
つまり 全てが静止する
交差点における
空白の３秒間といったところです
Conversely, there's never a time when they're all green. Unless a manufacturer was checking things.
逆に 信号が全て青になる
瞬間なんてものはありません
If I designed it, I'd build a system that couldn't do that at the structural level. Everyone prefers safe over dangerous.
それこそ 業者さんの
チェックでもない限りは
私が設計者なら
構造上そんなことができないように
システムを組み上げるでしょうね
誰だって 危険よりは
安全のほうがいいでしょう
Of course. No need to formally announce it.
（阿良々木）
そんなの 当たり前だろ？
改まって言うようなことじゃねえ
No, allow me to formally announce it. This is a pretty interesting story.
（扇）
いや 改まって言わせてください
これは結構 面白い話なんですよ
阿良々木先輩
When the world is filled with red lights signaling danger, the world is safer than usual.
危険を示す赤信号で
世界が満たされたときこそ
Timed Traffic Light
Safety                                          First
For Pedestrians
And Bicycles Only
いつよりも安全な時間であり
Danger
Please take photos inside the yellow area
Station Master
But when it's filled with green lights signaling safety, it creates a place more dangerous than anywhere.
逆に 安全を示す青信号で
世界が満たされたときは
Stop
世界のどこよりも 危険な場所が
出来上がってしまうという矛盾
Bicycles and Scooters
Beware of
Oncoming Traffic
Sidewalk
Do not park your vehicles
Workers Only
Car Frame
Division Chief
Access
Restricted
Such a contradiction.
（阿良々木）
健康にいい物が まずくって
Like how healthy food tastes awful, and something that tastes good is basically bad for you and makes you fat?
おいしい物は 基本的に
太りやすくて体に悪い
…みたいな話か？
Right. Like that.
（扇）
そうですね　そのとおりです
For someone so unintelligent, you're quick to understand.
頭が悪いくせに理解は早いですね
阿良々木先輩は
I'm honored by the praise.
お褒めにあずかり光栄の至りだよ
Sarcasm, not praise.
（扇）褒めてません　皮肉です
The world's full of people who think God's watching over them when they cross on green.
青信号を渡るときに
まるで神様に守られているような
気持ちでいる人ばかりですけれど
But in reality, that's not the case at all. It's merely that the risk is cut in half.
実は 全然そんなことは
ないんですよね
単にリスクが
半分に減ってるだけです
It's only slightly better than every light being green.
全部が青よりは ちょっとマシ
というくらいの話でしかないんです
If you don't want to face danger, don't cross any crosswalks.
危ない目に遭いたくなかったら
横断歩道を
渡らなければいいんですよ
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Sidewalk
Street
Light
Public
Road
Street Light
Sidewalk
Bollard
City Limits
Turntable
Entrance
Entrance Hall
Mail Corner
Management
Waste
Disposal
Mechanized Parking Lot
Bike/Minibike Parking Lot
Bicycle
Parking Lot
Bicycle Parking Lot
Canal
North
You say that, but the possibility of a drunk driver swerving into you on the sidewalk isn't zero either.
（阿良々木）
そんなこと言いだしたら
歩道を歩いていても
酔っ払い運転の車が蛇行して
突っ込んでくる可能性は
Sidewalk
Street
Light
Public
Road
Street Light
Sidewalk
Bollard
City Limits
Turntable
Entrance
Entrance Hall
Mail Corner
Management
Waste
Disposal
Mechanized Parking Lot
Bike/Minibike Parking Lot
Bicycle
Parking Lot
Bicycle Parking Lot
Canal
North
ゼロじゃないだろ？
Sidewalk
Street
Light
Public
Road
Street Light
Sidewalk
Bollard
City Limits
Turntable
Entrance
Entrance Hall
Mail Corner
Management
Waste
Disposal
Mechanized Parking Lot
Bike/Minibike Parking Lot
Bicycle
Parking Lot
Bicycle Parking Lot
Canal
North
Sidewalk
Street
Light
Public
Road
Street Light
Sidewalk
Bollard
City Limits
Turntable
Entrance
Entrance Hall
Mail Corner
Management
Waste
Disposal
Mechanized Parking Lot
Bike/Minibike Parking Lot
Bicycle
Parking Lot
Bicycle Parking Lot
Canal
North
Sidewalk
Street
Light
Public
Road
Street Light
Sidewalk
Bollard
City Limits
Turntable
Entrance
Entrance Hall
Mail Corner
Management
Waste
Disposal
Mechanized Parking Lot
Bike/Minibike Parking Lot
Bicycle
Parking Lot
Bicycle Parking Lot
Canal
North
Sidewalk
Street
Light
Public
Road
Street Light
Sidewalk
Bollard
City Limits
Turntable
Entrance
Entrance Hall
Mail Corner
Management
Waste
Disposal
Mechanized Parking Lot
Bike/Minibike Parking Lot
Bicycle
Parking Lot
Bicycle Parking Lot
Canal
North
Sidewalk
Street
Light
Public
Road
Street Light
Sidewalk
Bollard
City Limits
Turntable
Entrance
Entrance Hall
Mail Corner
Management
Waste
Disposal
Mechanized Parking Lot
Bike/Minibike Parking Lot
Bicycle
Parking Lot
Bicycle Parking Lot
Canal
North
Sidewalk
Street
Light
Public
Road
Street Light
Sidewalk
Bollard
City Limits
Turntable
Entrance
Entrance Hall
Mail Corner
Management
Waste
Disposal
Mechanized Parking Lot
Bike/Minibike Parking Lot
Bicycle
Parking Lot
Bicycle Parking Lot
Canal
North
Correct, that's not zero. But that's all the more reason to say stuff like this.
ええ ゼロじゃありません
でも だからこそ そんなことを
言いだすべきなのですよ
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Someone, such as myself, should be saying such things.
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
誰かが…
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
例えば 私が言いだすべきなのです
What a dangerous place this world is.
世の中というのが
どんな危険な場所なのか
Oh, how the world is peaceful. How it's full of dreams, hopes, and salvation.
世界は平和で
夢と希望にあふれていて
救いに満ちていて
How people were born to love each other and be friendly.
人と人は愛し合うために
生まれてきて
仲良くするべきで
How children are obligated to be happy.
子供には幸せになる義務があるとか
Since you're intoxicated in your speech as you blab that stuff, you're easily caught off guard.
そんなことを ぺちゃくちゃ
陶酔しながら言っているから
簡単に足元を すくわれるんです
Children in war zones, even without proper schooling, are more sound.
戦地の子供たちは
たとえ教育を受けていなくとも
もっと しっかりしていますよ
At least, they're more gluttonous about life.
少なくとも
人生に対しては貪欲です
In their eyes, all the signals they see are red, not green.
彼らの目には 青信号ではなく
赤信号ばかりが
映り込んでいますからね
In the end, Ougi-chan just wanted...
（阿良々木）
結局 このときの扇ちゃんは
...to teach me some trivia that all intersections have a three-second period where all lights are red.
“交差点で信号機が
全て赤になる時間は３秒”
というトリビアを
僕に教えたかった
I think she just wants to impress people,
自慢して感心されたかっただけ
らしいのだけれど
but the 15-year-old girl named Oshino Ougi turns such stories into massive tales of life and principles.
そんな話から 人生やら主義やらを
語ってしまうのが
忍野(おしの)扇という
15歳の女の子なのだった
And I'm reminded of that trivia alongside memories of Hachikuji Mayoi.
そして 僕は そんなトリビアを
八九寺真宵(はちくじ まよい)と共に思い出す
迷子の少女と共に思い出す
I'm reminded of those words along with a lost young girl.
Stress Test In Progress
Every traffic light in the way was red.
行く手をさえぎる
全ての信号機が赤色で
For Pedestrians
And Bicycles Only
And the instant she crossed on green, she was run over.
青信号を渡ったときにこそ
車にひかれた
I recall it with the memories of that girl who died over 10 years ago.
10年以上前に死んだ
あの女の子の思い出と共に思い出す
August 20th
That summer's epic adventure. Along with that story that started as a petty concept...
あの ひと夏の大冒険
ひどく ささいな
きっかけから始まり
...but in the end grew into a giant tale that almost engulfed everything that was real.
しかし 果ては現実の全てを
丸ごと巻き込まんばかりに
大きな話になってしまった
あの物語と共に…
Mayoi Jiangshi         Part One
Font used in the video: HGP Mincho B
Animation Number 71
20th of August
For Pedestrians
And Bicycles Only
If it isn't devil boy.
（斧乃木(おののき)）
あっ そこにいるのは
鬼のおにいちゃんじゃないか
You seem to be living well. I'm so at ease I'm jealous.
（斧乃木）
元気そうに生きているんだね
僕は安心して ねたましいよ
Hey, Ononoki-chan.
（阿良々木）よう 斧乃木ちゃん
For Pedestrians
And Bicycles Only
Been a while. Or... maybe not.
久しぶりってほどでもないのか
So...
えっと…
Kagenui
Thank you for using our services
Please form an orderly line
Stop
Kagenui
Wagon Sale
Six Floors
Bus Station
It's okay. You don't have to worry, devil boy.
心配しなくても大丈夫だよ
鬼のおにいちゃん
Onee-chan isn't with me. It's just me, Ononoki Yotsugi. In other words, I'm alone.
おねえちゃんなら一緒じゃない
ここにいるのは 斧乃木余接(よつぎ)
すなわち 僕１人さ
Information
Business Hours
Weekdays
11-21
Weekends
Holidays
11-20
It's not like Onee-chan and I always go everywhere together, devil boy.
別に 僕と おねえちゃんは
いつでも どこでも一緒にいる
というわけじゃないんだよ
鬼のおにいちゃん
Don't think of us as one set. We're merely a two-man cell.
僕たちはワンセットなんじゃなく
あくまでもツーマンセルさ
I see. Then that means you're pretty free for a shikigami.
ふ〜ん
For Pedestrians
And Bicycles Only
しかし とすると自由な式神だな
Come to think of it, weren't you alone and lost when we first met?
そういえば 初めて会ったときも
斧乃木ちゃん
１人で迷子になってなかったか？
Don't insult me. I just needed directions.
Information
Business Hours
Weekdays
11-21
Weekends
Holidays
11-20
侮辱しないでよ
僕は 道を聞いただけだ
The lost don't say that?
それを迷子と言うんじゃないのか？
If merely asking for directions makes you lost, no child in this world isn't lost.
道を聞いただけで
道に迷ったことになるのなら
世界に 迷子じゃない
子供なんていないよ
You know what they say.
ほら よく言うだろ？
Proverb
Animation Number 91
To ask is a moment's shame, but to not is lifelong.
“聞くは一時の恥
聞かぬは一生の恥”って
Proverb?
Animation Number 91
I suppose.
（阿良々木）まあ そうだな
They also say to teach is a moment's superiority, but to not is everlasting.
（斧乃木）
“教えるは一時の優越感”
“教えないは一生の優越感”
とも言うよね
Such a disgusting proverb doesn't exist.
（阿良々木）
そんな嫌な ことわざはない
Huh?
Animation Number 94
Hey, Ononoki-chan.
（阿良々木）なあ 斧乃木ちゃん
（斧乃木）何だい？
What?
Didn't you have a slightly stranger speech pattern last time I met you?
（阿良々木）
こないだ会ったときは
斧乃木ちゃんって
もう少し変なしゃべり方を
していたと思うんだけど
Didn't you always say, "I said with a posed look" after your lines?
ほら セリフの最後に常に
“僕はキメ顔で そう言った”
とか つけていたような
Shut up.
Business Hours
Weekdays
11-21
Weekends
Holidays
11-20
Business Hours
Weekdays
11-21
Weekends
Holidays
11-20
（斧乃木）黙れ
（阿良々木）うっ…
That is a black page in my history.
あれは僕の黒歴史
Selling All
Last Sale
Sixth Floor Special Hall
Selling Yukatas/Swimsuits
Information
Business Hours
Weekdays
11-21
Weekends
Holidays
11-20
I'll never make another posed look.
僕は二度と
キメ顔なんてしない
Rather, you never made one in the first place.
いや 別に元より
してなかったけどな
She realized it looked pitiful...
Animation Number 106
So, Ononoki-chan, what did you come to do?
で 斧乃木ちゃん
何をしに来たんだい？
Motto: Be nice to little girls.
Animation Number 106
To do? Come now, devil boy.
（斧乃木）何をしに？
おいおい 鬼のおにいちゃん
I don't really understand her archetype.
Animation Number 107
You say weird things.
おかしなことを言うじゃないか
Is this entire town your yard?
この町は あなたの庭かい？
She stopped with that weird tic,
Animation Number 107
I didn't know I needed permission to enter.
許可がないと立ち入り禁止
だったとは知らなかった
but I still have no idea what she's talking about sometimes.
Animation Number 107
My apologies.
こいつは失礼
Animation Number 108
It's not like it's my yard.
Last Sale
Sixth Floor Special Hall
Selling Yukatas/Swimsuits
Selling All
Information
Business Hours
Weekdays
11-21
Weekends
Holidays
11-20
別に僕の庭じゃないけど
Last Sale
Sixth Floor Special Hall
Selling Yukatas/Swimsuits
But it is my town. So if you're gonna do something strange here...
Selling All
Information
Business Hours
Weekdays
11-21
Weekends
Holidays
11-20
僕の町じゃあ ある
だから 斧乃木ちゃんが
妙なマネをしようっていうなら…
You'll get in my way?
（斧乃木）
邪魔をしようっていうのかい？
No, I thought I'd help you.
（阿良々木）
いや 手伝ってあげようかと思って
You're good-natured.
お人よしだね
Well, I came because someone called me. Dispatched you could say.
まあ 呼ばれたから来たんだよ
派遣されたと
言うべきかもしれないけれどね
As a shikigami, I don't know the details.
式神だけに
That sounds quite good.
Animation Number 117
詳細は知らない
By the way...
Information
Business Hours
Weekdays
11-21
Weekends
Holidays
11-20
（斧乃木）ところで…
（阿良々木）ん？
What about you? Where's your master?
鬼のおにいちゃんのほうこそ
ご主人様は どうしたんだい？
Wait, were you the master now? I don't know much.
いや 今は あなたのほうが
ご主人様なんだっけ？
よく知らないけれど
But anyway, you know, um...
とにかく あの… えっと
Oh, Shinobu.
ああ 忍(しのぶ)な
Information
Business Hours
Weekdays
11-21
Weekends
Holidays
11-20
Well, I'm not scared of that quasi-vampire at all.
（斧乃木）
まあ 僕は 全然あんな吸血鬼もどき
怖がっちゃいないけれどね
Animation Number 128
For Pedestrians
And Bicycles Only
Let's cross.
（阿良々木）渡ろうぜ
（斧乃木）うん
Business Hours
Weekdays
11-21
Weekends
Holidays
11-20
Business Hours
Weekdays
11-21
Weekends
Holidays
11-20
By the way, devil boy, this has been on my mind the whole time...
Ice
Ice Cream
（斧乃木）
ところで 鬼のおにいちゃん
ずっと気になっていたんだけれど
So    da
Gum
Candy
It's not negligence that I called to you, since it's on my mind.
それが気になって
鬼のおにいちゃんに
声をかけたと言っても
Animation Number 135
過失ではないんだけれど
You mean exaggeration.
Animation Number 135
（阿良々木）
〝過言〞だろ
Were you given that backpack?
そのリュックサック もらったの？
No, nobody gave this to me.
（阿良々木）
ああ いや もらったわけじゃない
Ice
Ice Cream
Hachikuji forgot this. She was at my place today. That careless girl forgot this in my room.
八九寺の忘れ物だ
今日 あいつが
僕の部屋に遊びに来てさ
そんときに あの うっかりさん
このリュックサックを
忘れていきやがったんだ
Hachikuji forgot it
Animation Number 143
You can forget backpacks?
Candy
忘れるんだね
リュックサックなんて
So here I am, chasing after her to deliver this to her.
Ice
Bubblegum
Ice Cream
Sweets for a Yen
（阿良々木）
それで 僕は それを届けるために
あいつを追いかけてる最中
ってわけさ
In any case, something left behind by a ghost... That's really, really unusual.
（斧乃木）
しかし 幽霊の忘れ物か
本当の本当に珍しいね
Gum
How'd she become a ghost in the first place?
そもそも あの子は どういう経緯で
幽霊になったんだい？
Beats me.
（阿良々木）さあね
I was human once too.
僕も元は人間なんだよ
（阿良々木）えっ？
Gum
Candy
Don't be so surprised. You used to be human yourself, right?
そんなに驚くことはないだろう
あなただって
元は人間なんだろう？
No, according to Onee-chan, you're still human, right?
いや おねえちゃんに言わせれば
今も人間なんだっけ
Who knows? It's a pretty vague concept.
So     da
さてな その辺は曖昧だが…
That's what Ononoki suddenly said.
Animation Number 159
It was quite shocking.
Like getting a confession out of the blue.
Animation Number 159
That reminds me. It wasn't made too clear last time. Ononoki-chan, what kind of aberration are you?
Ice
Bubblegum
Ice Cream
Sweets for a Yen
そういや その辺は こないだは
はっきりしなかったけれど
斧乃木ちゃん
君って何の怪異なわけ？
That's troublesome.
（斧乃木）何と聞かれても困るな
I'm a shikigami with quite a bit of original elements that Onee-chan created on her own.
おねえちゃんが
独自に作り出した—
オリジナル要素が相当に強い
式神だからさ 僕は
I think my basis is supposed to be a tsukumo-gami.
Ice
Bubblegum
Ice Cream
Sweets for a Yen
とはいえ 基礎としては 一応
付喪神(つくもがみ)ということになっている
Tsukumo-gami? You mean that?
（阿良々木）
付喪神？　って あれか…
Where tools used for 100 years gain a soul...
道具を百年続けて使ったら
魂を持つとか
百年を目前に捨てちゃったから
持ち主を恨むとか そういうやつか
...or there's a grudge because its owner tossed it out just shy of 100 years?
No?
違ったっけ？
That's pretty much accurate. But I'm a tsukumo-gami of a human.
大体 合ってるよ
Ice
Bubblegum
Ice Cream
Sweets for a Yen
ただし 僕は
人間の付喪神なんだけどね
A tsukumo-gami of a human used for 100 years.
百年使われた人間の付喪神
Ice
Bubblegum
Ice Cream
Sweets for a Yen
No, I guess it's like the tsukumo-gami of a corpse.
いや 死体の付喪神という感じかな
Though this is something Onee-chan tells me to keep secret.
Ice
Bubblegum
Ice Cream
Sweets for a Yen
まあ これは
おねえちゃんには秘密にしろと
言われていることだけれど
She said if I ever told anyone, she'd have to kill whoever I told.
誰かにバラしたら
そいつを殺さなくちゃ
ならなくなるからってさ
Is
Animation Number 168
what Ononoki-chan
said so disturbingly.
Animation Number 168
Then why give me this information?
（阿良々木）
てめえ なんて情報を
僕に流してくれるんだ
何か恨みでもあるのか？
Got a grudge? Don't take your frustration over Shinobu out on me.
忍の恨みを 僕で晴らすな！
No,
Animation Number 168
disturbing
isn't quite right
Animation Number 168
え？　じゃあ 斧乃木ちゃんって
Then, Ononoki-chan, you're actually over 100, yet look like a kid.
子供に見えて
百歳超えてるってこと？
Please, I'm not in that 75-and-over bracket.
まさか！
僕は そんな後期高齢者じゃない
What you'd call my "life" started when Onee-chan revived me.
僕の人生ってやつは
おねえちゃんに
生き返らせてもらったところから
始まってるんだ
Revived you?
生き返らせて？
Because I've died once already. I died and came back to life.
（斧乃木）
だから 僕は一度 死んでるんだよ
死んで生き返ったんだ
By the way, devil boy, can you tell what the difference between us is, in that sense?
ちなみに 鬼のおにいちゃん
僕と あなたの違いって
そういう意味では
果たして どこにあるか分かる？
Actually, include that ghost girl Hachikuji too.
いや 八九寺という
その幽霊の子も そうだけどさ
Difference? If you say difference, I think we're completely different.
違い？　違いっていうなら
全然違うと思うけれど
We all used to be human, but died in different ways.
みんな 元人間だけど
その死に方が違うのさ
In your case, you became immortal. You became immortal the instant you died.
鬼のおにいちゃんの場合は
不死身だ
死ぬと同時に
不死身になったんだよ
Strictly speaking...
つまり 厳密に言えば…
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
...you haven't died.
これは 死んでいない
ふむ
I, on the other hand, am dead. Really dead.
対して僕は死んでいる
本当に死んでいる
And am now back alive.
そして 死んだあとに
生き返っている
It's more correct to say I was reincarnated instead of revived.
生き返るというより
生まれ変わるというほうが
正しいんだと思う
Reincarnated?
生まれ変わり？
And in the case of that ghost girl, she hasn't come back to life.
そして あの女の子の幽霊の場合は
Dead, and staying dead without being revived. I think that's what a ghost is.
生き返っていない
死んで 生き返ることなく
死んだままだ
それが幽霊ということなんだろう
You don't continue to live and haven't been reincarnated. If anything, she continues to be dead.
生き続けてもいないし
生まれ変わってもいない
強いて言うなら 死に続けている
Animation Number 187
Hey, devil boy. When you think about it this way, who's the happiest of us?
ねえ 鬼のおにいちゃん
こうしてみると
誰がいちばん幸せなんだと思う？
All three of us, in our own ways, are lucky.
いや３人とも それぞれ それなりに
運のいいほうだと思うんだよ
I think you can say it's fortunate that we continue to be conscious even after death.
死んでも そのあとも
意識を保ち続けられるというのは
幸運と言ってもいいんだと思う
Animation Number 191
Can you generalize like that?
一概に そんなの
言えないんじゃないのか？
Have you ever thought about why you were born?
自分が何のために生まれてきたのか
って考えたことある？
I often thought about stuff like that in junior high.
中学生くらいのときに
そういうことは よく考えたぜ
I've thought about it since birth. Or more precisely, from the moment I died?
僕は生まれたときから
ずっと考えている
正確には死んだときから…
No, I've been thinking from the moment I was reincarnated. There has to be some meaning.
いや 生まれ変わったときから
ずっと考えてる
何か意味が
あるんじゃないかってね
If there's no purpose, I don't think I belong here.
そうでなければ ここにいちゃ
ダメな気がするんだ
Perhaps it's more about why I died.
それも 正確には
死んだ意味なのかな
I thought you might be able to answer that.
ひょっとすると あなたなら
答えられるかとも思ったけれど
I heard you stylishly declared your defiance against Onee-chan.
おねえちゃん相手に
随分と かっこいい
たんかを切っていたらしいし
No, I can't answer anything like that. And I don't think Hachikuji can either.
いや そんなこと
僕には答えられないし
八九寺にだって
答えられないと思うぜ
That is, if that's why you were asking how she became a ghost.
もしも そういう意味で
あいつが幽霊になった いきさつを
僕に聞いたんだったらだけど
Of course that's why.
もちろん そういう意味で聞いた
She had her own reasons to be lost. Lost in the real world.
（阿良々木）
あいつは あいつなりの
理由があって
As she ate her ice,
Animation Number 201
道に迷って
現世に迷っていたんだ
she talked about aberrations with a blank expression and asked me difficult questions.
Animation Number 201
That reason, or rather, objective, was already met over three months ago.
その理由っていうか
目的ってやつは
３か月以上前に
もう既に果たされたんだけれど…
Really? Then why does she continue to be a ghost?
そうなの？
じゃあ どうしてなお 彼女は
幽霊で あり続けているんだい？
Dunno.
さあ
Then, devil boy, if you see her again, ask her that for me.
じゃあ 鬼のおにいちゃん
その子に今度 会ったら
僕の代わりに聞いておいてよ
Ask her for you? What?
“聞いておいてよ”って 何を？
Isn't that obvious?
決まっているじゃないか
Whether or not she's happy as a ghost.
幽霊になって—
幸せかどうか
Animation Number 210
I couldn't find Hachikuji after all. It's not really a big deal
（阿良々木）
結局 僕は 八九寺を
見つけることはできなかった
なんのことはない
We have fun chats and interesting talks,
楽しく おしゃべりして
面白いトークを交わしていながらも
but I never understood her at all. I haven't been able to ask her the most important question.
僕は あいつと ちっとも
分かり合えちゃいないのだ
Reference
いちばん大事なことを
聞けずにいる
I'm sure I can't ask the question Ononoki-chan entrusted me with either. I can't ask her a thing.
斧乃木ちゃんに頼まれた質問も
きっと 聞けないだろうし
あいつには何も聞けない
Because she won't tell me anything.
あいつは 僕に
何も教えてくれないから
"What do you want to do?" "Where do your feelings lie?"
お前は どうしたいのか
お前の気持ちは どこにあるのか
"Is there anything you would like me to do?"
お前は 僕にしてほしいことは
何もないのか
There's so much I want her to tell me but can't bring myself to ask. I just want to grant all your wishes.
こんなに教えてほしいのに
聞けずにいる
お前の望みを
僕は かなえてやりたいのに
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Then go grant them. Why are you pretending to be worried about that, you fool?
（忍）
だったら かなえてやればよかろう
何を悩んどるフリを
しとるんじゃ このボケ
You know, nothing comes from worrying over things like that.
お前様よ そんなことで
悩んでも しかたなかろう
It's useless for you to ponder what that little girl wants to do or how she wants to be.
あの小娘が どうしたいのか
どうありたいのかなどと
お前様が考えても ムダなことじゃ
You shouldn't be asking that.
聞くべきでさえない
I shouldn't?
（阿良々木）聞くべきでさえ…
It's not like asking will do anything. Naturally, you'd wonder why you can't just grant that wish.
聞いたところで
どうにかできるわけでもあるまい
いきおい かなえてやれば
よいではないかと言ったものの
But you know better than anyone else that such a thing is impossible.
それが無理なことは
誰よりも お前様が
よく知っておるはずじゃろう？
What you should be worried about lies elsewhere.
お前様が悩むべきことは
もっと ほかにあるはずじゃ
No, no, you're a high-school student. A student's main duty is to study.
いやいや
お前様は高校生であろう？
学生の本分は勉強じゃ
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
I'm studying like I should.
勉強はしてるよ ちゃんと
You've been lurking in my shadow all summer break, so you know better than anyone.
夏休み中 ずっと僕の影に
潜んでいたお前が
誰よりも知っているはずだろうが
Well, I do know that. How you were hustling in your studies quite a bit...
（忍）いやあ 知っておるよ
お前様が 随分ハッスルして
勉強しておったことは
I was impressed that you were quite the student. I was literally cheering from the shadows.
大したもんじゃと
感心しておったよ
文字どおり
陰ながら応援しておったしの
But you know...
じゃが お前様
You haven't done any of your summer-break homework, have you?
夏休みの宿題
１個も やってないじゃろ？
（阿良々木）うっ
Animation Number 246
Textbook
Am I Nobita-kun?
僕は のび太くんかよ！
Help, Nobuemon!
助けて ノブえもん！
（忍）
何じゃ？
その 軽く ありそうな名前
What's with that name that sounds like it exists?
Only two hours until summer break ends.
（阿良々木）
残された夏休みは たった２時間
Nobuemon, give me a time machine. I'll hop in and go back a day.
おい ノブえもん
タイムマシンを
出してくれよ
ちょっと 昨日に
戻ってくるから
I understand adapting my name like it's in a Fujiko-sensei manga, but stop abbreviating my name as "Nobu."
藤子(ふじこ)先生風に
文字るのはかまわんが
お前様よ
忍を〝ノブ〞と
略すのは やめい
Then, Shinobu, give me a time machine.
（阿良々木）
じゃあ 忍
タイムマシンを出してくれ
As if!
（忍）出せるか！
Well, if you merely want to time-travel, I can be convinced to help out.
しかし まあ
時間移動がしたいと言うのならば
協力せんでもないぞ
Huh?
（阿良々木）え？
You want to go back to yesterday, right?
（忍）昨日に戻りたいんじゃろ？
Let's do it!
やっちゃお！
Animation Number 265
Is time warping that easy?
タイムワープって
そんな簡単に できるもんなのか？
I was on a groove and came as told, but this is totally a sci-fi world.
ノリで ここまで 言われるがままに
ついてきちゃったけれど
完全にＳＦの世界じゃねえか
Are you an idiot? If there are aberrations out there, time travel exists as well.
（忍）アホか お前様は
怪異があるなら
時間移動もあるじゃろ
And I was dubbed king of aberrations, one that kills aberrations,
（忍）
しかして わしは
怪異の王とまで呼ばれた—
怪異殺しの怪異
there's nothing I can't do if I try.
やって できんことはないわ
Really now?
Animation Number 273
That sounds
fishy.
Animation Number 273
Animation Number 274
All right. These shrine gates should be good enough.
よし！　まあ この鳥居でよかろう
O red shadows that govern chaos!
“混沌(こんとん)を支配する赤き闇よ”
I summon the sphere that toys with the flow of time!
“時の流れを もてあそぶ球体を
いざ招かん”
Repeat forth the lights of weekends that come and go!
“めぐりにめぐる
週末のともしびを ただ繰り返し”
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
And fill the skies with overflowing thunder!
“あふれ出す いかずちで
空を満たせ”
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Walkers of the black! Swimmers of the gray!
“黒を歩む者 灰を泳ぐ者”
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
With the mourning name filled with sin, thou shalt become the carrier!
“罪深き その忌み名をもって
自らを運び屋とせよ”
Count me surprised!
Animation Number 288
A blast from the past!
Animation Number 282
We don't have
that sort of acting anymore.
Animation Number 282
Jet Black
Animation Number 285
Blackness
Darkness
Animation Number 285
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
I took a step back out of uneasiness.
Animation Number 294
Even my spirit waned.
I almost fainted.
Animation Number 294
Is this linked to an alternate dimension or something?
何だよ？　異次元にでも
つながってんのかよ これ
Of course.
（忍）まあ そうじゃが
This went well for my first time!
初めてやってみたが
うまくいくもんじゃのう
Impressive, even after losing my powers and turning into a girl.
幼女になり 力をほとんど
失ったとは言っても
さすが わしじゃわい
But wait. If you can create an alternate dimension, I don't think that counts as losing your powers.
（阿良々木）しかし どうだ？
異次元を生じさせるほどの
力があるんだったら
それって力を失ったって
言わなくないか？
It's not my powers. It's the location's.
わしの力ではない
場の力じゃ
I just converted the ghastly energy...
あの不愉快な
アロハ小僧が言うところの
...that the unpleasant Hawaiian-shirt boy would call essences for aberrations gathered into heat energy.
寄り集まった怪異の素みたいな
霊的エネルギーを
軽く熱エネルギーに
コンバートしただけの話じゃ
What's that pseudoscience?
なんだよ そのエセ科学
We should hurry though.
ちゅうか 急いだほうがよいぞ
I don't think I can open this gate another time. It will close in a minute.
このゲート
もう一度は 多分 開けん
あと１分もすれば
閉じてしまうぞい
（阿良々木）
１分？　ちょっと待てよ
まだ心の準備ができてない
A minute? Hold on, I'm not mentally ready.
No need to be ready. Just jump in like normal.
準備など いらん
普通に飛び込めばよい
Heh? It's that easy?
（阿良々木）
え？
そんな簡単でいいの？
It's not something to brace yourself over. It's merely time travel.
（忍）
そう身構えることでは
ないのじゃ
たかが
時間移動じゃろうが
Shinobu seems rather cheery,
Animation Number 307
rather unworried to me,
so the dangers are... probably... not great.
Animation Number 307
Okay, let's go!
オーケー じゃあ行くか！
Yeah! On our way!
（忍）おう！　出発！
Oh yes. You.
あっ そうじゃ お前様
（阿良々木）何だよ？
What?
No, that watch.
（忍）いや その時計…
（阿良々木）ん？
That watch.
（忍）その腕時計
Your watch that you wrap on your right wrist for vanity even though you're not left-handed. Lend me that.
左利きでもないくせに見栄を張って
右手首に巻いておる—
お前様の その腕時計
ちょっと貸せい
No need for such detail. I get it.
（阿良々木）
そこまで細かく説明しなくっても
分かるわ
Doubt
Animation Number 316
But why?
（阿良々木）え？　なんで時計を？
（忍）いいから
Just give it to me.
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
（阿良々木）ん？
（忍）何をしとるんじゃ？
What are you doing?
Don't get nervous from this.
（忍）
いや この程度で
ドギマギするでないわ
We go to the bathroom and take baths together. We're always together.
トイレも一緒 風呂も一緒
四六時中
生活を共にしておるくせに
For someone serious like me, holding hands makes me nervous no matter how long it's been.
（阿良々木）
いや… でも
異性と手をつなぐというのは
僕のような
生真面目な人間にとっては
いつまでも ドギマギするもんで…
Hush. Hurry up and jump. I have a shallow sense of time, so I have to match your cornering maneuvers.
（忍）やかましい！
ほれ さっさと飛び込め
わしは 時間の観念が薄いので
お前様のコーナリングに
付き添っていくしかないのじゃ
Oh, I see. I get it. You can't do it by yourself.
（阿良々木）ああ そうなんだ
なるほど
１人じゃ できないのか
All right. I'll take you there, Shinobu! To an unknown world!
（阿良々木）
いいだろう
連れていってやるぜ 忍
未知の世界へな！
Animation Number 332
When we passed through the shrine gate,
Animation Number 334
I didn't think about something as selfish as going back to the day before,
but instead reflected on Hachikuji.
Animation Number 334
Hey, you, wake up. Don't pass out from such a light shock as this.
（忍）
おい お前様よ 起きろ！
この程度のショックで気絶するな
（阿良々木）ん…
ん… えっと
Um...
What time is it?
あれ？　今 何時？
Noon. Midday.
（忍）12時じゃ 昼のな
This is about halfway up the mountain?
ここは 山の中腹辺りか
Did we really time-travel?
で 本当に
時間移動に成功したのか？
Of course we succeeded.
（忍）
成功したに決まっておろうが
I've never failed at anything since birth.
わしは 生まれてこの方
失敗したことがない
How much more blatantly can you brag?
（阿良々木）
大言壮語も はなはだしいな お前
But still, I think August 19th was a bright, sunny day like this.
しかしな ８月19日も
こんな感じの晴天だった気がするし
No, isn't it just that I fell down the stairs and passed out for 12 hours?
いや 普通に階段から落ちて
12時間
気絶してただけじゃねえのか？
That would be a problem.
Animation Number 352
Not only is my homework not done, I'd also have ditched the opening ceremony.
Hanekawa will kill me...
Animation Number 352
Hey, Shinobu.
なあ 忍
What?
何じゃ？
Do we use those shrine gates to go back?
（阿良々木）
帰りも あの鳥居から
帰ればいいのか？
（忍）
ん？　ああ…
まあ そんな感じじゃ
Yup. Something like that.
Why's your answer so vague?
（阿良々木）
なぜ返事が曖昧なんだよ？
（忍）いや そういえば
Come to think of it, we didn't put much thought into the return trip.
あんまり帰りのことを
考えてなかったのじゃが…
And come to think of it, to open a gate to time warp,
（阿良々木）
そういえば
タイムワープするゲートとやらを
こじ開けるためには
she said it wasn't her powers but the location's. The energy drift known as North Shirahebi Shrine.
忍自身の力ではなく
北白蛇(きたしらへび)神社という吹きだまり
場の力を利用したと言っていたが
Now that we spent those powers, maybe you can't open that gate again, by chance?
（阿良々木）
その力を消費してしまった以上
ひょっとして
もう そのゲートとやらを
開くことは
できないんじゃないのか？
Animation Number 362
Well...
え〜っと
Hey, wait, Shinobu.
（阿良々木）
おい！　ちょっと待て 忍
まさか…
We're not in a situation where we can't go back to our world from this one, right?
昨日の世界から元の世界へと
帰れないなんて事態に
陥ってんじゃねえだろうな？
No, it's fine! It's all right! Nothing to worry about, my master.
（忍）
いや 大丈夫じゃ 大丈夫じゃ
我が主(あるじ)様
何の心配もいらぬ
Now think about it. This world is yesterday, right?
ほれ 考えてもみい
ここは昨日の世界じゃぞ？
Looking at it from here, I opened the time tunnel using the essences of aberrations from tomorrow.
わしが 神社にたまる
怪異の素を利用して
タイムトンネルを開いたのは
つまり 今から見れば
明日ということになろう
So those ghastly energies haven't been used at this point, so I can open that gate.
じゃから 現時点では
まだ その霊的エネルギーは
使用されておらん
ということじゃから
ゲートは開ける
Huh? Doesn't that create a time paradox?
（阿良々木）
あれ？　それって
タイムパラドックス生じてねえか？
If we use that energy today, we can't come back to today from tomorrow.
今日 もし僕たちが
そのエネルギーを使ってしまえば
明日の僕たちが
今日に戻って来られないじゃないか
Uhuh.
Animation Number 368
She said nothing.
She didn't know what to say.
Animation Number 368
Five minutes later
Well...
え〜っとなあ
Shinobu's opinion
Animation Number 369
Oh, right! Now I remember!
そうじゃ！　思い出した　そうそう
It takes less energy to return to the future compared to going to the past.
未来へ戻るのは 過去に戻るよりも
使うエネルギーが少ないのじゃ
Because we don't go against the flow. Same basic concept as salmon.
流れに逆らわん分だけな
サケと同じ原理じゃ
Animation Number 372
So we won't be using that much energy for the return trip.
（忍）
じゃから 帰り道にあたっては
そこまでのエネルギーを消費せず
So there will be enough energy left over for us to come here tomorrow.
明日 わしたちが
ここに来るための分くらいの
エネルギーは
残っておるということじゃ
Doubt
Animation Number 373
（阿良々木）
ふ〜ん
Doubt
Honestly, though, it did make me think.
Animation Number 373
I thought about the somewhat dangerous implications of time paradoxes.
What type of time warp was this anyway?
大体 このタイムワープって
どういうタイプなんだ？
Type? What do you mean?
（忍）
タイプ？　どういう意味じゃ？
There are generally two kinds of time warp.
（阿良々木）
いや タイムワープって
大きく分けて２種類あるじゃん
Animation Number 376
One where the traveler exists and one where they don't.
つまり
本人がいるタイプと
Animation Number 376
本人が いないタイプ
What? You mean like your standings within your high school classroom?
なんじゃ
高校の教室における
お前様の立場みたいなもんか？
I'm always there!
Animation Number 378
僕は
いつだって いるよ！
I don't fade in and out of existence!
Animation Number 378
In other words, I'm asking if "yesterday's me" is home now,
つまりだ 僕が家に帰れば
“昨日の僕”ってヤツがいるのか
or if the me standing here is already "yesterday's me."
それとも ここにいる僕が
既に“昨日の僕”なのかって話だ
（いびき）
（阿良々木）寝るな！
Don't snooze!
Red Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Hmm. I don't understand it well.
ふん！　よく分からんが
A man
shouldn't
sweat the
details.
A man
shouldn't
sweat the
details.
But you can go confirm it for yourself. Go home and look at your room.
そんなことは じかに見て
確認すればよかろう
うちに帰って 自分の部屋を見て
そこに自分がいるか いないかで
And whether or not you're there will show which type this is.
どちらのタイプなのかは
判明するじゃろう
I guess so.
（阿良々木）まあ そうだな
Wait, huh? Shinobu, how do you know what time it currently is?
えっと あれ？
でも 忍 なんでお前
今の時間が分かるんだ？
（忍）ん？
（阿良々木）だって—
I mean that watch is from the future, so it's not showing the correct time for this world, right?
お前の巻いている その時計は
未来から来た物なんだから
この時代の正しい時間を
示しているわけじゃないだろう？
I adjusted it earlier by guessing what time it was based on the sun.
（忍）
いやいや
さっき アジャストしたのじゃ
太陽の位置で時間を推測しての
It's troublesome to not know the time, which is why I had you take this watch off and borrowed it.
時間が分からんと困るので
じゃから お前様に
この時計を外させ 借りたのじゃよ
ふ〜ん
Let's go home for now.
まあ とりあえず
うちに帰ってみようぜ
Oh, then can I ride on your shoulders? Can I?
（忍）
あっ！　じゃあ じゃあ じゃあ
肩車 肩車！
So cute!
（女子中学生１）
やだ なに？　かわいい！
She's like a doll!
（女子中学生２）お人形さんみたい
Her hair is so fluffy!
（女子中学生３）
髪の毛なんか ふわっふわだ！
Um, you, can you tell me something? Is today Monday, August 21st?
ねえ 君たち
ちょっと教えてほしいんだけど
今日って８月21日の月曜日？
Huh? Not even close!
（女子中学生１）
ええ？　全然違いますよ
Then what's today's month and day?
（阿良々木）
じゃあ 今日って何月何日だい？
What's with you, mister? You sound like you came from the future!
（女子中学生２）
何ですか？　おにいさん
まるで未来から
来た人みたいなことを…
It's May 13th.
５月13日ですよ
Is what they said.
Animation Number 398
I'll be damned.
13th of May
What year is it right now counting in Western years?
今 西暦で言えば
何年？
Well...
（女子中学生３）えっと…
The junior-high girl replied...
（阿良々木）
女子中学生は答えた
...with the year eleven years prior to the present, or what is now the future.
今から あるいは未来から
11年前の西暦を…
Preview
Dialogue Script - Nisio Isin
4-Koma Illustrations - Haritama Hiroki
Preview
Karen here!
（火憐(かれん)）火憐だぜ！
（月火(つきひ)）月火だよ！
And Tsukihi!
I'm Tsukihi!
Together, we're the Fire Sisters!
We're the Fire Sisters!!
Slant
（月火･火憐）
２人合わせて
“ファイヤーシスターズ”！
We won't be the Fire Sisters forever you know.
You've lost your shell?
（月火）
だけど 私たち いつまでも
ファイヤーシスターズじゃないよね
Eh? What kind of ad lib is that? Do you want to quit on me all of a sudden?
（火憐）
えっ いきなり何？　そのアドリブ
なに？　辞め時ってこと？
That's not it. I just think maybe it's time to advance to the next stage.
（月火）
いや そうじゃなくて
そろそろ 次なるステージに
Found it!
向かうときじゃないかと
言いたいのさ
（火憐）
次なるステージ！
The next stage?
I, Tsukihi-chan, think it's time we became the Fire Systems!
（月火）
ファイヤーシステムズになるときが
来たんじゃないかと
月火ちゃんは思うのだよ
It was an easy case this time.
（火憐）
ファイヤーシステムズ？
Fire Systems? What do you know, it sounds so cool!
何それ？
スゲえ かっこいいじゃん！
No foe will stand before our Fire System. Everything's going according to plan.
（月火）
私たちのファイヤーシステムの前に
敵はない！　フフッ
全て計算どおりですよ
Well, let's go back!
Yay us! Retrieving lost items is easy!
Fire Sisters Power!
（火憐）
スゲえ！　月火ちゃんが
頭脳キャラみたいに
Smart Tsukihi-chan is awesome!
（月火）
フフ　スベっても計算どおりですよ
That was also part of the plan.
（火憐）
一気にギャグキャラみたいに…
Now you're just being silly...
Next time! Kabukimonogatari Episode 2!
Next Time
Mayoi Jiangshi Part 2
（火憐･月火）
次回「傾(かぶき)物語」
第２話「まよいキョンシー其ノ貮(そのに)」
Mayoi Jiangshi, Part 2.
By the way, I'm always trying to be the smarter one.
We're lost and can't find our way home!
（月火）
っていうか 私 今でも
頭脳キャラのつもりなんだけど…
Does that mean your plans have failed in the past?
（火憐）
じゃあ 計算違いが
あったんじゃねえか？